+34 682 39 81 69

martinez.javier@gmail.com

Avinguda de la Rca Argentina 261 5-2, 08023, Barcelona, Spain

# **Javier Martinez Canillas**

# **Summary**

I'm a software engineer with experience working on different layers of the Linux software stack, ranging from the kernel to user-space applications.

Also, I'm an open-source enthusiast that contributes to many open source projects specially the Linux kernel where I maintain a couple of components (https://www.openhub.net/accounts/martinezjavier).

#### **Specialties**

Software engineering, Linux user-space and kernel development, System integration, Packaging.

### **Education**

2010 - 2011

Master of Science (M.Sc.), High Performance Computing - Universitat Autónoma de Barcelona, Bellaterra, Spain.

Thesis: Including the Workload Effect in the Parallel Program Signature.

Advisor: Prof. Emilio Luque.

2002 - 2008

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Informatics Engineering - Catholic University "Nuestra Señora de la Asunción", Asunción, Paraguay.

**Thesis:** A new approach to solve Multi-Objective Evolutionary Optimization Problems using Linear Genetic Programming.

Advisor: Prof. Benjamín Barán.

# **Awards and Honors**

PIF-UAB predoctoral scholarship for Master of Science studies at Universitat Autónoma de Barcelona.

# **Professional Experience**

#### January 2012 - Present

Senior Software Engineer - Collabora (http://www.collabora.co.uk)

- Helped customers to upstream their Linux kernel platform support, work close to mainline and reduce their maintenance burden.
- Developed customer specific Linux distributions using the OpenEmbedded/BitBake build system and Debian/Ubuntu derivatives using Debian packaging and the Open Build Service (OBS).
- Improved the Desktop Bus (D-Bus) inter-process communication system performance by developing a new socket address family (AF\_BUS) for multicast communications on Linux.

Repository: http://cgit.collabora.com/git/user/javier

# September 2011 - January 2012

Linux Kernel Engineer - ISEE (http://www.isee.biz): Embedded systems manufacturer.

■ Linux kernel device drivers and bootloader (X-loader and U-boot) development for custom ARM OMAP3 (Cortex-A8) based boards.

Repository: http://git.igep.es/

#### October 2010 - August 2011

M.Sc. Student, Professor and Researcher - Computer Architecture and Operating System department, Universitat Autónoma de Barcelona.

- Design and implementation of a parallel application performance analysis and prediction tool.
- Doing research to improve the tool accuracy.
- Teaching assistant for the course "Electronic systems design based on microcontrollers".

# July 2009 - September 2010

Professor and Researcher - Computer Engineering, Polytechnic Faculty, National University of Asunción.

■ Updated the Linux Device Drivers 3 book examples to compile and run with newer kernels. So students can develop their own virtual device drivers based in those examples:

Repository: https://github.com/martinezjavier/ldd3

 Developed a sniffer as a kernel module using the kernel's protocol handler (struct packet\_type) kernel infrastructure to help students understand packet reception. ■ Developed a firewall as a kernel module using netfilter register hooks API (*struct nf\_hook\_ops*) to help students understand data structures used by the kernel to store frames (*struct sk\_buff*) and headers (*struct iphdr*, *struct tcphdr*, *struct ethhdr*).

#### Open source contributions

May 2010 - Present

Kernel hacker - Linux kernel (http://git.kernel.org)

Mainline maintainer of the OMAP3 IGEP embedded board family and the TI OMAP GPIO driver.

https://www.openhub.net/accounts/martinezjavier

#### **Publications in Journals and Conferences**

- [1] Javier Martinez Canillas. Kbuild: the Linux Kernel Build System, The Linux Journal, 2012.
- [2] Martinez Canillas, J. and Wong, A. and Rexachs, D. and Luque, E. Including the Workload Effect in the Parallel Program Signature. High Performance Computing and Communications (HPCC), 2011 IEEE International Conference on. September, 2011, Banff, Canada.
- [3] Martinez Canillas, J. and Wong, A. and Rexachs, D. and Luque, E. Predicting Parallel Applications Performance using Signatures: the Workload Effect. Computer Systems and Applications (AICCSA), 2011 IEEE/ACS International Conference on. December, 2011, Sharm El-Sheikh, Egypt.
- [4] R. Sánchez, J. Martinez, B. Barán. Macro-Economic Time-Series Forecasting Using Linear Genetic Programming, 11<sup>th</sup> Joint Conference on Information Sciences, Dec 15-20, 2008, China.
- [5] Javier Martinez Canillas, Roberto Sánchez, Benjamín Barán. Estimation Models Generation using Linear Genetic Programming. CLEI Electronic Journal Volume 12 Number 3, December 2009. Regular Issue and Special Issue of Best Papers presented at CLEI 2008, Santa Fe, Argentina.